Finding Aid for Henry Howland Crapo Papers 1830-1920
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Howland Crapo Papers 1830-1920
Crapo, Henry Howland, 1804-1869.
Flint, Michigan industrialist; governor of Michigan, 1865-1868. Correspondence concerning land speculations, lumbering, and political activities; correspondence of his son primarily relating to estate and land holdings; speeches, notes and other papers detailing his gubernatorial administration; deeds and other papers concerning land purchases in Ohio, Iowa, and Michigan; newspaper clippings, biographical material and obituaries; journals, diaries, notebooks, letter book, political scrapbook, 1866-1869, executive journal of state of Michigan, 1865-1867, farm records and accounts; and photographs.
851633 Aa 2; AC; Ac
15 microfilms 6.5 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
5.5 linear feet
3 oversize volumes not microfilmed
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection came to the library in 1935, donated by Henry Howland Crapo, Governor Crapo's grandson (donor number 1162 ). Additions were received in 1940, coming from Henry and William Crapo, Crapo's son (donor number 1060 ).
The collection is open for research.
Henry Howland Crapo, a native New Englander, served as mayor of the city of Flint, state senator for the 24th District, and governor of Michigan. His activities in the private sector, however, were perhaps as crucial to Michigan as his years spent in public service. Contemporaneously with his action in state politics, Crapo was one of the entrepreneurial businessmen who helped make Michigan the leading lumber producer of the nation for nearly three decades.
Henry Crapo was born at Dartmouth, Massachusetts on May 27, 1804 to a poor farming family. Henry, however, quickly exhibited the ambition and ability which would later mark his endeavors in Michigan. As a young man, he took control of the local schoolhouse and when it became a high school he became its principal.
In 1832, Crapo moved to New Bedford, Massachusetts, where he taught himself the trade of surveying. In New Bedford he held many public offices and helped found the state's first free public library. He displayed a keen interest in horticulture and began investing in Michigan's pine lands in 1837. In 1856, after further investing in Michigan's timber resources, Crapo moved to Flint to better care for his business endeavors.
Once in Flint, Crapo devoted himself to developing one of the state's largest and most successful lumber businesses. He opened lumber manufacturers in Flint, Fentonville, Holly, and Detroit, and was instrumental in building the Flint & Holly Railroad. Once established in the community, Crapo served terms as Flint's mayor and represented his district in the state senate.
Crapo earned the respect and admiration of his fellow citizens and business associates alike, and in 1865 he was elected governor of Michigan. In 1868, riding a wave of popularity, he was elected to a second term.
Crapo's time at the state's helm was marked by his personal integrity and faithful service to the public. He earned admiration when he vetoed bills granting railroad aid legislation. His action in the railroad matter, though struck down by the state senate, was upheld by the Supreme Court. He was an active Republican from the time of the party's organization.
Crapo and his wife, Mary Ann (Slocum), had ten children. Their only son, William Wallace Crapo, would become a U.S. Congressman from New Bedford, Massachusetts. Henry Crapo died on July 27, 1869, after a long and debilitating illness.
The Crapo papers have been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Personal and Biographical; Political; Business records; and Miscellaneous (mainly financial). The collection relates primarily to the career of Henry H. Crapo with the files dating after 1869 pertaining to the business activities and political activities of his son W. W. Crapo.
In 1992, the bulk of the Crapo papers was microfilmed. This finding aid begins with a listing of the contents of the microfilm followed by a container listing of those portions of the collection which were not microfilmed. For reasons of preservation, the researcher should use the microfilm copy. Access to the original materials will be limited to the unmicrofilmed portions of the Crapo papers.
Subjects:
Adrian (Mich.); Agriculture--Michigan.; Anti-Saloon Republican National Committee.; Crapo, Henry Howland, 1804-1869.; Elections--Michigan--1862.; Elections--Michigan--1864.; Elections--Michigan--1866.; Fairfield (Mich.); Fentonville (Mich.); Flint (Mich.); Flint and Holly Railroad Company.; Flint and Pere Marquette Railway Company.; Governors--Michigan.; Isle Royale Mining Company.; Jackson, Lansing and Saginaw Railroad Company.; Kalamazoo County (Mich.); Kalamazoo and Schoolcraft Railroad Company.; Land use--Michigan.; Lenawee County (Mich.); Logging--Michigan.; Lumbering--Michigan.; Macomb County (Mich.); Marathon (Mich.); Marquette & Ontonagon Railroad Company.; Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1845-1860.; Michigan--Politics and government--1861-1865.; Michigan--Politics and government--1866-1876.; Monroe County (Mich.); Odessa (Mich.); Railroads--Michigan.; Real estate business--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Roads--Michigan.; Saginaw and Lansing Rail Road Company.; Salt industry and trade--Michigan.; United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 3rd (1861-1866); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Yellowstone National Park.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Crapo, Henry Howland, 1804-1869.; Crapo family.; Governors--Michigan.
Contributors:
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth), 1841-1915.; Bacon, Daniel S., 1839-1866.; Baker, Orrin.; Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866.; Christiancy, Isaac Peckham, 1812-1890.; Crapo, David.; Crapo, Stanley T.; Crapo, William Wallace, 1830-1926.; Driggs, John F., 1813-1877.; Driggs, William S.; Duffield, D. Bethune (Divie Bethune), 1821-1891.; Fenton, William M., 1808-1871.; Giddings, Orrin N., 1814-1904.; Gilman, Daniel Coit, 1831-1908.; Green, Noah K., 1808-1886.; Joy, James F. (James Frederick), 1810-1896.; Kellogg, John R., 1793-1868.; Leach, DeWitt C., b. 1832.; Ledyard, Henry, 1812-1880.; Mears, Charles B., 1814-1895.; Mercer, William, b. 1824.; Pitcher, Zina, 1797-1872.; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.; Smith, Humphrey Henry Howland Crapo.; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866.; Standish, John H., b. 1816.; Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1814-1869.; Trowbridge, Rowland E., 1821-1881.; Turner, James.; Ward, Eber Brock, 1811-1873.; Warner, William, 1812-1868.; Williams, Harvey, 1812-1867.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.; Wisner, Moses, 1815-1863.; Withey, Solomon L., 1820-1886.; Woodman, Jonathan J., b. 1825.
Genre/Form:
Christmas cards.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Stereographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1836-1839 (Reel 1)
  - 1840-1842 (Reel 1)
  - 1843-1844 (Reel 1)
  - 1845-1846 (Reel 1)
  - 1847-1848 (Reel 1)
  - 1849 (Reel 1)
  - 1850 (Reel 1)
  - January-June 1851 (Reel 1)
  - July 1851 (Reel 1)
  - August-September 1851 (Reel 1)
  - October-December 1851 (Reel 1)
  - January-April 1852 (Reel 1)
  - May-August 1852 (Reel 1)
  - September-October 1852 (Reel 1)
  - November-December 1852 (Reel 1)
  - January 1853 (Reel 1)
  - February 1853 (Reel 1)
  - March 1853 (Reel 1)
  - April 1853 (Reel 1)
  - May 1853 (Reel 1)
  - June 1853 (Reel 1)
  - July 1853 (Reel 2)
  - August 1853 (Reel 2)
  - September 1853 (Reel 2)
  - October 1853 (Reel 2)
  - November 1853 (Reel 2)
  - December 1853 (Reel 2)
  - January 1854 (Reel 2)
  - February 1854 (Reel 2)
  - March 1854 (Reel 2)
  - April 1854 (Reel 2)
  - May 1854 (Reel 2)
  - June 1854 (Reel 2)
  - July 1854 (Reel 2)
  - August 1854 (Reel 2)
  - September 1854 (Reel 2)
  - October 1854 (Reel 2)
  - November 1854 (Reel 2)
  - December 1854 (Reel 2)
  - January 1-15, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - January 16-31, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - February 1855 (Reel 3)
  - March 1-15, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - March 16-31, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - April 1-20, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - April 21-30, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - May 1855 (Reel 3)
  - June 1855 (Reel 3)
  - July 1855 (Reel 3)
  - August 1855 (Reel 3)
  - September 1855 (Reel 3)
  - October 1-15, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - October 16-31, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - November 1-15, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - November 16-30, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - December 1-15, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - December 16-31, 1855 (Reel 3)
  - January 1856 (Reel 4)
  - February 1856 (Reel 4)
  - March 1856 (Reel 4)
  - April-May 1856 (Reel 4)
  - June 1856 (Reel 4)
  - July 1856 (Reel 4)
  - August 1856 (Reel 4)
  - September-November 1856 (Reel 4)
  - December 1856 (Reel 4)
  - January-March 1857 (Reel 4)
  - April-June 1857 (Reel 4)
  - July-September 1857 (Reel 4)
  - October-December 1857 (Reel 4)
  - January 1858 (Reel 4)
  - February-March 1858 (Reel 4)
  - April 1858 (Reel 4)
  - May 1858 (Reel 4)
  - June-August 1858 (Reel 4)
  - September-December 1858 (Reel 4)
  - January-February 1859 (Reel 5)
  - March-May 1859 (Reel 5)
  - June-August 1859 (Reel 5)
  - September-December 1859 (Reel 5)
  - January-March 1860 (Reel 5)
  - April-June 1860 (Reel 5)
  - July-August 1860 (Reel 5)
  - September-December 1860 (Reel 5)
  - January 1861 (Reel 5)
  - February-March 1861 (Reel 5)
  - April-May 1861 (Reel 5)
  - June-July 1861 (Reel 5)
  - August-September 1861 (Reel 5)
  - October 1861 (Reel 5)
  - November 1861 (Reel 5)
  - December 1861 (Reel 5)
  - January 1862 (Reel 5)
  - February-March 1862 (Reel 5)
  - April-May 1862 (Reel 5)
  - June-August 1862 (Reel 5)
  - September-October 1862 (Reel 5)
  - November-December 1862 (Reel 5)
  - January-February 1863 (Reel 6)
  - March 1863 (Reel 6)
  - April 1863 (Reel 6)
  - May 1863 (Reel 6)
  - June 1863 (Reel 6)
  - July-August 1863 (Reel 6)
  - September-October 1863 (Reel 6)
  - November-December 1863 (Reel 6)
  - January-February 1864 (Reel 6)
  - March 1864 (Reel 6)
  - April 1864 (Reel 6)
  - May-June 1864 (Reel 6)
  - July 1864 (Reel 6)
  - August 1864 (Reel 6)
  - September-October 1864 (Reel 6)
  - November-December 1864 (Reel 6)
  - January-February 1865 (Reel 6)
  - March 1865 (Reel 6)
  - April 1865 (Reel 6)
  - May-June 1865 (Reel 6)
  - July 1865 (Reel 6)
  - August-September 1865 (Reel 6)
  - October 1865 (Reel 6)
  - November-December 1865 (Reel 6)
  - January 1866 (Reel 7)
  - February 1866 (Reel 7)
  - March 1866 (Reel 7)
  - April-May 1866 (Reel 7)
  - June 1866 (Reel 7)
  - July 1866 (Reel 7)
  - August-September 1866 (Reel 7)
  - October-November 1866 (Reel 7)
  - December 1866 (Reel 7)
  - January 1867 (Reel 7)
  - February 1867 (Reel 7)
  - March 1867 (Reel 7)
  - April 1867 (Reel 7)
  - May 1867 (Reel 7)
  - June-July 1867 (Reel 7)
  - August 1867 (Reel 7)
  - September 1867 (Reel 7)
  - October-December 1867 (Reel 7)
  - January 1868 (Reel 7)
  - February-March 1868 (Reel 7)
  - April 1868 (Reel 7)
  - May-June 1868 (Reel 7)
  - July-August 1868 (Reel 7)
  - September 1868 (Reel 7)
  - October 1868 (Reel 7)
  - November-December 1868 (Reel 7)
  - January-February 1869 (Reel 8)
  - March-April 1869 (Reel 8)
  - May-July 1869 (Reel 8)
  - August 1869 (Reel 8)
  - September-December 1869 (Reel 8)
  - 1870-1875 (Reel 8)
  - 1876 (Reel 8)
  - January-March 1877 (Reel 8)
  - April-June 1877 (Reel 8)
  - July-September 1877 (Reel 8)
  - October-December 1877 (Reel 8)
  - January-March 1878 (Reel 8)
  - April-May 1878 (Reel 8)
  - June-August 1878 (Reel 8)
  - September-October 1878 (Reel 8)
  - November-December 1878 (Reel 8)
  - January-March 1879 (Reel 8)
  - April-June 1879 (Reel 8)
  - July-December 1879 (Reel 8)
  - January-March 1880 (Reel 8)
  - April-June 1880 (Reel 8)
  - July-December 1880 (Reel 8)
  - January-February 1881 (Reel 8)
  - March-June 1881 (Reel 8)
  - July-December 1881 (Reel 8)
  - January-March 1882 (Reel 9)
  - April-December 1882 (Reel 9)
  - January-April 1883 (Reel 9)
  - May-December 1883 (Reel 9)
  - 1884 (Reel 9)
  - 1885 (Reel 9)
  - 1886 (Reel 9)
  - 1887 (Reel 9)
  - January-June 1888 (Reel 9)
  - July-October 1888 (Reel 9)
  - November-December 1888 (Reel 9)
  - January-February 1889 (Reel 9)
  - March-June 1889 (Reel 9)
  - July-December 1889 (Reel 9)
  - 1890-1891 (Reel 9)
  - 1892-1894 (Reel 9)
  - January-April 1895 (Reel 9)
  - May-September 1895 (Reel 9)
  - October-December 1895 (Reel 9)
  - January-April 1896 (Reel 9)
  - May-August 1896 (Reel 9)
  - September-December 1896 (Reel 9)
  - January-April 1897 (Reel 9)
  - May-September 1897 (Reel 9)
  - October-December 1897 (Reel 9)
  - January-February 1898 (Reel 9)
  - March-December 1898 (Reel 9)
  - 1899 (Reel 9)
  - 1900-1901 (Reel 10)
  - 1902 (Reel 10)
  - 1903 (Reel 10)
  - 1904 (Reel 10)
  - 1905-1920 (Reel 10)
- Personal and Biographical
  - J.C. Willson's synopsis and daily notes on the care of H.H. Crapo (Reel 10)
  - Record of his last illness kept by H.H. Crapo (Reel 10)
  - Resolutions on death of Crapo (Reel 10)
  - Last will and testament of H.H. Crapo (Reel 10)
  - Obituaries of Crapo (Reel 10)
  - Biographical notes on Crapo made by his son W.W. Crapo (Reel 10)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - 1852 1859 (Reel 10)
    - 1860-1866 (Reel 10)
    - 1867 (Reel 10)
    - 1868-1869 (Reel 10)
    - Undated (Reel 10)
    - Re agriculture and general conditions in Michigan (Reel 10)
- Political
  - Notes for political campaigns 1861-1863 (Reel 10)
  - Notes on various subjects pertinent to Crapo's term in the State Senate (Reel 10)
  - Notes on agriculture and general conditions in Michigan assembled by Crapo as background for the governorship (Reel 10)
  - Miscellaneous papers concerning Crapo's governorship (Reel 10)
  - List of pardons made by Crapo 1865-1866 (Reel 10)
  - Papers concerning Crapo's Railroad Bill vetoes (Reel 10)
  - Papers concerning Crapo's 1866 campaign (Reel 10)
  - Report 1866 of the Adjutant General of the United States on the status of the Michigan militia (Reel 10)
  - Notes and papers on the Negro suffrage amendment (Reel 10)
  - Notes for Thanksgiving proclamation (Reel 10)
  - Speeches and articles
    - Notes for speeches to soldiers (Reel 10)
    - Draft of address on agriculture delivered at Flint October 11, 1861 (Reel 11)
    - Campaign address 1864 (Reel 11)
    - Notes and other materials for political campaign speeches 1864 (Reel 11)
    - Message to the Legislature circa 1867-1868 (Reel 11)
    - Final message to the Legislature January 1869 (Reel 11)
    - General (Reel 11)
    - Manuscript of articles on the draining of swamps and raising of Hereford cattle (Reel 11)
    - Manuscript of an address by H.H. Crapo to Genesee County Agricultural Society (Reel 11)
    - Address of W.W. Crapo 1919 (Reel 11)
  - Political notebook stating plan of campaign for election of 1864 (Reel 11)
  - State Military Agency, Soldier's Relief Fund 1865-1866 (Reel 11)
  - Executive Journal of State of Michigan
    - January 4, 1865-December 20, 1866 (Reel 11)
    - August 29, 1866-December 31, 1868 (Reel 11)
  - Scrapbook 1866-1869 on second gubernatorial term (Reel 12)
- Business records
  - Memorandum books dealing chiefly with lumbering activities
    - 1854-1856 (Reel 12)
    - 1855-1856 (Reel 12)
    - 1856-1857 (Reel 12)
    - 1857-1858 (Reel 12)
    - 1857-1859 (Reel 12)
    - 1859 (Reel 12)
    - 1860 (Reel 12)
    - 1863-1864 (Reel 12)
  - Notebooks, journals, and diaries of H.H. Crapo
    - 1844-1845 (Reel 12)
    - March 23, 1851-March 18, 1858 (Reel 12)
    - 1853-1854 (Reel 12)
    - 1854 (Reel 12)
    - October 24, 1857-April 8, 1858 (Reel 12)
    - March 16, 1858-November 12, 1859 (Reel 12)
    - November 14, 1859-December 31, 1860 (Reel 12)
    - 1861 (Reel 12)
    - 1862 (Reel 12)
    - 1863 (Reel 12)
    - 1864 (Reel 12)
    - Lake Superior Memorandum July 11, 1865 (Reel 13)
    - 1867 (Reel 13)
    - 1868 (Reel 13)
    - 1869 (Reel 13)
    - 1874 (Reel 13)
    - 1875 (Reel 13)
    - 1877 (Reel 13)
    - 1878 (Reel 13)
    - 1879 (Reel 13)
  - Letter Press Books of H.H. Crapo
    - July 6, 1853-February 25, 1854 (Reel 13)
    - February 25, 1854-November 25, 1854 (Reel 13)
    - November 27, 1854-June 16, 1855 (Reel 14)
    - June 14, 1855-February 6, 1856 (Reel 14)
    - August 24, 1855-August 15, 1856 (Reel 14)
    - August 16, 1856-March 8, 1858 (Reel 15)
  - Land indentures (Reel 15)
    (also includes some proclamations, maps, broadside)
- Miscellaneous (mainly financial)
  (These files have not been microfilmed)
  - Dated Miscellaneous
    - 1827-1845 (Box 5)
    - 1846-1848 (Box 5)
    - 1849-1852 (Box 5)
    - 1853-1856 (Box 5)
    - 1857-1859 (Box 5)
    - 1860-1866 undated (Box 5)
  - National Loan Fund Insurance Society 1847-1850 (Box 5)
  - First Michigan land purchase 1835 (Box 5)
  - Ohio lands 1836-1851 (Box 5)
  - Personal and business cards 1858-1859 (Box 5)
  - Iowa lands 1878-1890, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Purchase of the Driggs tract, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - H.H. Crapo's settlement with James Arnold, his original partner, in December 1859, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Purchase of James Arnold's interest in the Flint Mill Property (Box 6)
  - Sash factory account 1867-1868 (Box 6)
  - Flint yard stock account 1868 (Box 6)
  - Flint and Pere Marquette Railroad earnings statement 1890 (Box 6)
  - Michigan pine lands 1850-1884
    - General 1850s-1860s, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Land description and tract maps, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Maps and broadsides, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Journal of W.W. Crapo lands 1878-1884 (Box 6)
  - Eber B. Ward will 1874 (Box 6)
  - Eber B. Ward lands, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - E.B. Ward loan bonds 1873-1897, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - H.P. Platt account 1878-1901
    - Taxes on Ottawa and Lucas County lands 1878-1881 (Box 6)
    - Articles of agreement 1879 (Box 6)
    - Land sold and taxes paid 1879-1884 (Box 6)
    - H.P. Platt account 1878-1894 (Box 6)
    - Sale of Ottawa County land; unsold land; special account A (Box 6)
    - Cancelled contracts 1879-1890 (Box 6)
    - Agreement for sale of Ohio lands 1879-1885 (Box 6)
    - Lucas County land 1881-1885 (Box 6)
    - Agreement on Ward lands 1897 (Box 6)
    - Statement (Ward lands) 1899-1900 (Box 6)
    - Final settlement 1894 (Box 6)
    - Land contract 1901 (Box 6)
    - Warranty deed 1902 (Box 6)
  - Auction cards dealing with the sale of Hereford cattle (Box 6)
  - Awards for purebred cattle (Box 6)
  - Receipts and vouchers
    - 1820-1825 (Box 6)
    - 1826-1830 (Box 6)
    - 1831-1832 (Box 6)
    - 1833-1834, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1834-1835, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1835, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1836 (Box 7)
    - 1837, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1838 (Box 7)
    - 1839, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1840, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1841, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1842, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1843-1844 (Box 7)
    - 1844, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - 1844-1847 (Box 7)
    - 1845-1846, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - 1847-1848, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - 1849-1850 (Box 7)
    - 1850-1851, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1851, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1852-1853 (Box 7)
    - 1863-1868 (Box 7)
    - Undated (Box 7)
  - Receipts
    - 1844-1845 ("Roundville lot") (Box 7)
    - 1843-1845 (Rockwell estate) (Box 7)
    - 1842-1844 (Tucker South Lot) (Box 7)
    - 1842-1845 (Whittemore, Bassett and Tucker lots) (Box 7)
    - 1842-1845 (Tucker North Lot) (Box 7)
    - 1844-1846 (Thacher lot), 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1845 (Mill pond) (Box 7)
    - 1845 (house and barn) (Box 7)
    - 1845-1846 (Acushnet Quarry) (Box 7)
    - 1846-1847 (Turpentine Lot) (Box 7)
    - 1841-1899 (Building at Marathon) (Box 7)
  - Bills
    - 1846, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - 1848, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - 1849-1850, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - 1851-1852, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - 1855-1856, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 1855-1857, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Sundry cash payments April 1856-April 1858 (Box 8)
  - Farm bills 1888 (Box 8)
  - Farm accounts 1889-1894, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Land records, deeds, tax deeds, mortgages (Box 9)
  - Exchange of Facilities between the Pere Marquette and the Pennsylvania Railroads in and between Toledo and Detroit (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 9)
  - Memorandum books dealing chiefly with lumbering activities
    - 1854-1856 (Box 10)
    - 1855-1856 (Box 10)
    - 1856-1857 (Box 10)
    - 1857-1858 (Box 10)
    - 1857-1859 (Box 10)
    - 1859 (Box 10)
    - 1860 (Box 10)
    - 1863-1864 (Box 10)
  - Notebooks, journals, and diaries of H.H. Crapo
    - 1844-1845 (Box 10)
    - March 23, 1851-March 18, 1858 (Box 10)
    - 1853-1854 (Box 10)
    - 1854 (Box 10)
    - October 24, 1857-April 8, 1858 (Box 10)
    - March 16, 1858-November 12, 1859 (Box 10)
    - November 14, 1859-December 31, 1860 (Box 10)
    - 1861 (Box 10)
    - 1862 (Box 10)
    - 1863 (Box 10)
    - 1864 (Box 10)
    - Lake Superior Memorandum July 11, 1865 (Box 10)
    - 1867 (Box 10)
    - 1868 (Box 10)
    - 1869 (Box 10)
    - 1874 (Box 10)
    - 1875 (Box 10)
    - 1877 (Box 10)
    - 1878 (Box 10)
    - 1879 (Box 10)
  - Swamp lands notebook concerning building contracts, etc. 1865 (Box 11)
  - Memorandum and account books for various Massachusetts properties of H.H. Crapo 1841-1851, 14 volumes (Box 11)
  - Farm journals and ledgers for Crapo farm 1890-1902, 14 volumes (Box 11)
  - Farm Journals and ledgers 1888-1889, 2 volumes (Box 12)
  - Stock breeding record books, 2 volumes (Box 12)
  - Indices to letters received by H.H. Crapo August 1853-April 1856 (Box 12)
  - Notebooks concerning E.B. Ward lands, Ottawa and Lucas County lands, and record of logs sawed in 1869, 5 volumes (Box 12)
  - Photographs (Box 12)
  - Journals, 3 oversize volumes (Volume 1)
Selective Index to Correspondents and Subjects
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth), 1841-1915.
Letter, Nov. 29, 1887, to H.H. Crapo, about Crapo speaking before the Providence Board of Trade.
Anti-Saloon Republican National Committee.
Correspondence and circular, 1888, of the Anti-Saloon Republican National Committee.
Bacon, Daniel S., 1839-1866.
Letters of Nov. 5, 1855 and Dec. 13, 1855, chiefly on land matters.
Baker, Orrin
Letters, Sept. 2, 1845, Jan. 6, 1846, Sept. 7, 1846, Apr. 13, 1847, Aug. 9, 1847, Aug. 16, 1847, Jan. 17, 1848, Aug. 22, 1849, Sept. 25, 1849, and throughout the 1850s of Orrin Baker of Fairfield, Lenawee Co., Michigan about Crapo's land dealings in that area; also includes full and frequent comments on local news, weather, agriculture, etc.
Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866.
Letter, April 1854, from P. W. Nims discussing Cass's railroad and land interests in Michigan.
Christiancy, Isaac Peckham, 1812-1890.
Nine letters, 1855-1856, from Isaac Christiancy dealing with land purchases and holdings in Monroe County; and one letter on railroad matters.
Crapo, David
Letters, 1853-1855, to Crapo from his brother David, who settled in Odessa, Michigan as a farmer and wrote fully about conditions there.
Crapo, Stanley T.
Correspondence of Stanley T. Crapo, grandson of H. H. Crapo, 1890s, mostly on matters connected with the Crapo farm near Flint.
Crapo, William Wallace, 1830-1926.
Letters from and to W. W. Crapo throughout the correspondence. The papers and correspondence from 1869 on are principally those of W. W. Crapo dealing mostly with business matters pertaining to his father's estate, but including some general correspondence, 1888-1890, while W. W. Crapo was a member of Congress from Massachusetts
Driggs, John F., 1813-1877.
Copy of a letter, April 15, 1864, of John Driggs, congressman about Crapo's candidacy for governor.
Driggs, William S.
Correspondence and other material of and relating to William S. Driggs, owner of the Driggs tract which was purchased by Crapo and associates in 1855 and marked the beginning of Crapo's lumbering career.
Duffield, D. Bethune (Divie Bethune), 1821-1891.
Letters, Jan.-Feb. 1867, from D. B. Duffield to Henry Crapo on railroad matters.
Elections-- Michigan--1862.